<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[hallucinations]]></title><description><![CDATA[by anshuman sahoo]]></description><link>https://anshu92.github.io/blog</link><image><url>/images/cover/coll.jpg</url><title>hallucinations</title><link>https://anshu92.github.io/blog</link></image><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Jul 2018 00:39:04 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://anshu92.github.io/blog/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[An ode to the Art of software engineering]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>Coming from a background that sees software as a tool for ‘higher’ purposes - for example, signal processing, hardware engineering and machine learning, the past few months working on various software projects have revealed the amount of thought and design that needs to go into the tooling so that the ‘higher’ goals can be seamlessly expressed and swooned on. Having to deal with inefficiencies and issues with projects has often felt like patching a machine gunned pot of water. And no amount of technical hijinks and quantum mechanics has been able to solve the problems - which has led me to believe that perhaps the technical hammer of Thor is not the only superpower I need.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And so I reluctantly picked up ‘Code Complete’ and tried to elevate my skills from ‘Coder’ to ‘Software Engineer’. After a few pages, I had highlighted almost every line. This is because every salient point seemed to alleviate a pain point I had encountered in the last few months. I felt like a physicist who didn’t know Newtonian physics swinging pendulums in random ways.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Over the next few months, I hope to blog more on the lessons I learn as I try to become better at this job as well as about my interests. For now, I wanted to share my incredulity at the aliquot perspective I had about my own work.</p>
</div>
<div class="quoteblock">
<blockquote>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>“There is a pleasure in the pathless woods,</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>There is a rapture on the lonely shore,</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>There is society, where none intrudes,</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>By the deep Sea, and music in its roar:</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I love not Man the less, but Nature more,</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>From these our interviews, in which I steal</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>From all I may be, or have been before,</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>To mingle with the Universe, and feel</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>What I can ne’er express, yet cannot all conceal.”</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Lord Byron</p>
</div>
</blockquote>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>&#8201;&#8212;&#8201;Anshu</p>
</div>]]></description><link>https://anshu92.github.io/blog/2018/07/02/An-ode-to-the-Art-of-software-engineering.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://anshu92.github.io/blog/2018/07/02/An-ode-to-the-Art-of-software-engineering.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Software Engineering]]></category><category><![CDATA[ Insight]]></category><category><![CDATA[ Personal]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Anshuman Sahoo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>