<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Untitled RSS Feed]]></title><description><![CDATA[Untitled RSS Feed]]></description><link>https://anshu92.github.io/blog</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 07:43:32 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://anshu92.github.io/blog/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[First Post]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="https://anshu92.github.io/blog/images/christmasprofile.JPG" alt="Christmas Profile" width="400" height="300">
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Hi, welcome! I am a 24 year old guy living in Toronto. I am interested in a lot of things like technology, the interconnectedness of things, the human brain, music, books and esoteric adventures.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I wished to chronicle my growth as a person as well as leave a record for psychologists to examine in case&#8230;&#8203;well, just in case. I also feel obligated to put my glorious adjustment to anti epilpetic drugs over the past year as a reason for this journaling activity. (Been taking an epileptic drug called Tegretol since I was 10 &#8594; Slowed my brain down for a few years coincinding with my years in university &#8594; Now I m back and with a rejuvinated spirit for learning and fighting the power, which is still my brain lol)</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>That&#8217;s a good segue to tell everyone about my current employment situtation. I spent the last 6 months working for a startup that builds tools for epileptics. I was developing seizure detection algorithms for them, but for various reasons I quit a couple of weeks ago. I still think they ll be a successful company because their mission is pretty complimentary to the needs of 1 in 26 people in this world (Check them out : <a href="http://www.neutun.com/" class="bare">http://www.neutun.com/</a>). I worked on their seizure detection algorithms and testing. Here&#8217;s what i did : <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Es_uIpyG4FE" class="bare">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Es_uIpyG4FE</a> . Anyway, I have been interviewing to join a few cool projects in machine learning, which is a field that has caught me right in its gaze of unfiltered possibilities. I had an interview with Qualcomm last Friday which went pretty alright and I&#8217;m hopeful.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>So yes, that&#8217;s where I am - partially glad to be spending this Canadian winter in the comforts of my room and working on personal projects including a rigorous quest to achieve physical optimization.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I have a few blog posts coming up - a book review and about the Gross National Happiness idea in Bhutan. So I hope wanderers and friends will come back and read my thoughts on those.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Soon.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Anshuman<br>
Toronto<br>
17 Jan 2017</p>
</div>]]></description><link>https://anshu92.github.io/blog/2017/01/17/First-Post.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://anshu92.github.io/blog/2017/01/17/First-Post.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Introduction]]></category><category><![CDATA[ Personal]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Anshuman Sahoo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>