<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Flowers for Anshuman]]></title><description><![CDATA[blog by anshuman sahoo]]></description><link>https://anshu92.github.io/blog</link><image><url>/images/cover/collage.jpg</url><title>Flowers for Anshuman</title><link>https://anshu92.github.io/blog</link></image><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 May 2017 21:25:22 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://anshu92.github.io/blog/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Book Review: Flowers of Algernon]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>I had stopped reading fiction for a while, but I came across this book and the setup intrigued me. I saw a rat in my building a few days ago and it freaked me out, and that&#8217;s why I guess the cover attracted my attention.</p>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="https://anshu92.github.io/blog/images/flowersforalgernonbook.jpg" alt="Book cover">
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I bought the audiobook and started listening to it on the way to work. My commute is 20 minutes, and the book is such a gripping tale that I wished it was longer.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I strangely, or maybe not strangely empathize a lot with Charlie Gordon, the 32 year old protagonist of this book. He is a mentally challenged boy working in a bakery. He has been picked to be part of an experiment at the local college and he writes progress reports chronicling his understanding of what is being done to him. What hits you about the way the author narrates the book is the first thing you notice about the book. The voice and language matches Charlie&#8217;s as he progresses or digresses throughout.
Charlie is a good natured simpleton would be the way to put it. Or rather he is that kind, sensitive ten year old kid who has been mentally stationary as the rest of him grows older.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The story moves as Charlie starts responding to treatment and starts becoming smarter by the day. It exposes a lot of falsehoods, beliefs and opinions we treat as absolute when we interact we people we consider normal. It reveals the insignificance of the human ego, the neglect of the gifts we are bestowed by being born as a living creature with this configuration or programming. It also reveals the problems with the importance we place on non-existential things like superiority, pride and titular accomplishments.It reveals the great need of connecting with another through the emotion and bonding of love.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The inflection point occurs when Charlie seems to surpass his 'creators' in terms of intelligence and finds himself having only one other person who understands his situation - Algernon, the mouse who has undergone the same treatment as him. He realizes that brain power is not a substitute for emotional growth, and that whether a result of tribalism borne out of evolutionary necessity, or an inevitable accident of co-existence, human interaction is irrational and perhaps too multi-variate. The characters around him feel like a cast of a play - the kind, conflicted heroine played by Alice Kinnian, who was Charlie&#8217;s teacher and was perhaps the first to see Charlie as a human rather than a guinea pig, or a mouse. Faye, the carefree, artiste neighbor in contrast wanted life free of structure and pay heed to only primal urges. Dr.Strauss, with whom Charlie has therapy session - supportive, humane and predictable. Dr. Nemur, the guy in charge of the experiment - consumate academic, sees Charlie with the same eyes as he sees Algernon. Charlie&#8217;s family - they play a melodramatic side of Charlie&#8217;s flashbacks that help illustrate the difficulties of dealing with issues of people with various intelligence living together. Their repentance and joy when Charlie meets them during the intelligent phase is to me the place where the book tries to overplay its hand.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The book decides to become a tragedy as Charlie discovers that the permanence of his intelligence predicted by Dr.Nemur is infact not true and that his intelligence will fade soon. He notices erratic behavior from Algernon, and the rest of teh book is about solidifying his conclusions about human behavior and making sure that his legacy is impactful for people like him.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The book is a work of art in terms of narrative quality and in providing a perspective about the humanity in everyone.</p>
</div>
<div class="ulist">
<ul>
<li>
<p>Anshuman
Toronto
07/05/2017</p>
</li>
</ul>
</div>]]></description><link>https://anshu92.github.io/blog/2017/05/07/Book-Review-Flowers-of-Algernon.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://anshu92.github.io/blog/2017/05/07/Book-Review-Flowers-of-Algernon.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Books]]></category><category><![CDATA[ Fiction]]></category><category><![CDATA[ Thinking]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Anshuman Sahoo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 07 May 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Annotations:Daniel Kahneman: "Thinking, Fast and Slow" | Talks at Google]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="ulist">
<ul>
<li>
<p>Intuition - favorable view vs skeptical. Important question in medicine evidence based ve intuitive application of medicine.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Two ways of thinking -</p>
<div class="ulist">
<ul>
<li>
<p>passive - {perception, feelings, intuition} we are not authors of passive thinking.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Active - {doing math, procedural}..pupils dilate by 50% when we concentrate. Effortful..limited capacity to exert effort.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</div>
</li>
<li>
<p>A bat and a ball together cost 1.10. Bat costs 1 more than ball. How much does ball cost? Most people see the question and answer 10 cents. The correct answer is 5 cents. Most people dont check their math and trust intuition.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Does not like ‘magic of intuition’ propagated by Malcolm Gladwell’s Blink. Intuition = Recognition</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Is the world regular enough to develop recogntion? Chess players world is regular. Contant feedback allows us to learn rules..ex. Know a friends mood from the way he speaks.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>[<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homunculus" class="bare">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homunculus</a>](<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homunculus" class="bare">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homunculus</a>)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>[<a href="https://www.amazon.ca/Moonwalking-Einstein-Science-Remembering-Everything/dp/0143120530/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1485375427&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=moonwalking+with+einstein" class="bare">https://www.amazon.ca/Moonwalking-Einstein-Science-Remembering-Everything/dp/0143120530/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1485375427&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=moonwalking+with+einstein</a>](<a href="https://www.amazon.ca/Moonwalking-Einstein-Science-Remembering-Everything/dp/0143120530/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1485375427&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=moonwalking+with+einstein" class="bare">https://www.amazon.ca/Moonwalking-Einstein-Science-Remembering-Everything/dp/0143120530/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1485375427&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=moonwalking+with+einstein</a>)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Memory is bad at lists, really good at remembering routes through spaces. People are good tthinking about agents..agents have traits and behaviors..we form global impressions of personalities. We are bad at understanding sentences with abstract subjects. This is why he uses systems to explain how we think even though its disapproved by psychologists. Ref: homonculus</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Circular reinforcing systems - Sticking a pencil in your mouth to make a smile makes cartoons appear funnier.Associations done in system 1/associative memory.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Associative memory works on new stimuli by making everything coherent.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="https://anshu92.github.io/blog/images/kahneman_1.PNG" alt="Psych test 1">
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>In this psychology experiemnt mind reads first as B and second as 13 even though both are identical. We get coherent interpretation while the ambiguity is supressed.</p>
</div>
<div class="ulist">
<ul>
<li>
<p>When an upper class british voice says I have a large tattoo on my back or a man says I m pregnant, we characteristically register surprise. The system 1 classifies world knowledge at top speeds as normal or abnormal. Brain is trained to think along causal lines.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>When instructed to perform an operation, we often perform extra operations..we compute more than need to..allowing substitutions to take place</p>
</li>
</ul>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="https://anshu92.github.io/blog/images/kahneman_0.png" alt="Psych test 2">
</div>
</div>
<div class="ulist">
<ul>
<li>
<p>Which of the three figures is larger on the screen? Ans: they are equal. But we see right one as bigger..because we automatically compute 3D version of the pic. Another example is the dating heurestic. Ask first how happy u are and then how many dates you ve had? When order is reversed of asking..ppl associate dates with happiness by 0.66</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Based on the fact that a girl is able to read at age 4, ppl are asked what her GPA is? Most ppl get impression of precocity from her reading ability, match that to a relative percentile of able readers at age 4..ad the mind automatically matches that percentile to a GPA of 4, which is statistically absurd. This is oe of the mechanisms that leads to intuitive errors&#8230;&#8203;this kind of mechanism of substitution.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Subjective confidence - propobability of being correct is a feeling we have..it is actually assessing the fluency of its own processing; assesing the coherence of its own story it has created. This is disastrous because you can concoct stories out of little informatio or unreliable info that seems coherent. People can be confident for very little reason.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Kahneman’s book : <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/11468377-thinking-fast-and-slow" class="bare">https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/11468377-thinking-fast-and-slow</a>
Link to talk : <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CjVQJdIrDJ0" class="bare">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CjVQJdIrDJ0</a></p>
</div>]]></description><link>https://anshu92.github.io/blog/2017/01/25/Annotations-Daniel-Kahneman-Thinking-Fast-and-Slow-Talks-at-Google.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://anshu92.github.io/blog/2017/01/25/Annotations-Daniel-Kahneman-Thinking-Fast-and-Slow-Talks-at-Google.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Psychology]]></category><category><![CDATA[ Brain]]></category><category><![CDATA[ Thinking]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Anshuman Sahoo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[First Post]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="https://anshu92.github.io/blog/images/christmasprofile.JPG" alt="Christmas Profile" width="400" height="300">
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Hi, welcome! I am a 24 year old guy living in Toronto. I am interested in a lot of things like technology, the interconnectedness of things, the human brain, music, books and esoteric adventures.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I wished to chronicle my growth as a person as well as leave a record for psychologists to examine in case&#8230;&#8203;well, just in case. I also feel obligated to put my glorious adjustment to anti epilpetic drugs over the past year as a reason for this journaling activity. (Been taking an epileptic drug called Tegretol since I was 10 &#8594; Slowed my brain down for a few years coincinding with my years in university &#8594; Now I m back and with a rejuvinated spirit for learning and fighting the power, which is still my brain lol)</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>That&#8217;s a good segue to tell everyone about my current employment situtation. I spent the last 6 months working for a startup that builds tools for epileptics. I was developing seizure detection algorithms for them, but for various reasons I quit a couple of weeks ago. I still think they ll be a successful company because their mission is pretty complimentary to the needs of 1 in 26 people in this world (Check them out : <a href="http://www.neutun.com/" class="bare">http://www.neutun.com/</a>). I worked on their seizure detection algorithms and testing. Here&#8217;s what i did : <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Es_uIpyG4FE" class="bare">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Es_uIpyG4FE</a> . Anyway, I have been interviewing to join a few cool projects in machine learning, which is a field that has caught me right in its gaze of unfiltered possibilities. I had an interview with Qualcomm last Friday which went pretty alright and I&#8217;m hopeful.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>So yes, that&#8217;s where I am - partially glad to be spending this Canadian winter in the comforts of my room and working on personal projects including a rigorous quest to achieve physical optimization.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I have a few blog posts coming up - a book review and about the Gross National Happiness idea in Bhutan. So I hope wanderers and friends will come back and read my thoughts on those.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Soon.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Anshuman<br>
Toronto<br>
17 Jan 2017</p>
</div>]]></description><link>https://anshu92.github.io/blog/2017/01/17/First-Post.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://anshu92.github.io/blog/2017/01/17/First-Post.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Introduction]]></category><category><![CDATA[ Personal]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Anshuman Sahoo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>